[Music]
although total fasting can dramatically
increase blood levels of the stress
hormone cortisol as much as doubling
within five days
just dieting alone
does not
there is however a way stress and
obesity could turn into a vicious cycle
weight stigma
across thousands of individuals followed
for four years those reporting
discriminatory experiences had more than
twice the odds of becoming obese and
those who started out obese had more
than three times the odds of staying
that way compared to those who started
out at the same weight but didn't
experience discrimination now this could
be from stress-induced eating on one
side of the calorie balance equation or
stigma induced exercise avoidance on the
other obese individuals with more
frequent experiences with weight stigma
report greater avoidance of exercising
in public feeling judged and embarrassed
these two fat exercise fears may be well
grounded strong anti-fat biases have
been documented in both fitness
professionals and regular gym goers
which may translate into an unwelcoming
environment in fitness centers and
health clubs
whichever side of the calorie equation
gets tipped those who experience weight
stigma can also end up suffering health
consequences independent of any added
weight those reporting more frequent fat
prejudice exhibit higher levels of
depression higher levels of inflammation
and higher levels of oxidative stress as
well as a shorter life span
two studies following a total of nearly
20 000 people both found about a 50
increase in mortality risk among those
reporting greater daily discrimination
weight discrimination may shorten
life expectancy
despite these hazards some scholars
advocate for even more fat shaming
the president emeritus of the
prestigious hastings center infamously
advocated for a kind of stigmatization
light using social pressures to compel
people to lose weight without resorting
to outright discrimination after all he
argued what else has the potential to
counter the persuasive force of the
billions spent in advertising every year
by the food and beverage industry it
worked against tobacco
he recalls his own battle with addiction
the force of being shamed and beat upon
socially was as persuasive for me to
stop smoking as the threats to my health
the public health campaign to stigmatize
cigarettes turned what had been
considered simply a bad habit into
reprehensible behavior
when such campaigns have been tried
they've been met with fierce resistance
though
georgia's strong for life campaign
featured billboards of morose-looking
obese children with captions like
warning chubby kids may not outlive
their parents or
it's hard to be a little girl
when you're not
the campaign sponsors defended the ads
as an attempt to break through the
denial in a state with some of the
highest recorded childhood obesity rates
it's only defensible though if it works
yale researchers found that when normal
weight women are provided with bowls of
m ms jelly beans and chips to snack on
after
watching clips of stigmatizing material
like clumsy loud lazy stereotypes
getting teased about their weight
they eat about the same amount compared
to watching neutral material such as
insurance commercials but when
overweight women watch the same two sets
of videos they triple their calorie
intakes after watching the stigmatizing
scenes
the researchers concluded this directly
challenges the notion that pressure to
lose weight in the form of wheat stigma
will have a positive motivating effect
on overweight individuals
in other words it could make things
worse
being labeled too fat in childhood was
associated with a higher risk of
becoming obese compared to children
weighing the same who were never told
that
but does that mean we should just ignore
the elephant in the room
many doctors apparently think so
just as veterinarians have been found to
be reluctant to tell people their pets
are obese fewer than a quarter of
parents of overweight children report
having been told by pediatricians about
their child's weight status
one might think it would be obvious but
a gallup survey found that parents
appear to be notoriously poor judges of
their children's weight
similarly the percentage of adults who
describe themselves as overweight has
remained essentially unchanged over the
past few decades despite skyrocketing
obesity
all this gallup concluded helps paint a
picture of mass delusion in the united
states
about its rising weight
i
think patients have the right to be
informed those told by their doctor that
they are overweight have about four
times the odds of attempting weight loss
and about twice the odds of succeeding
just as smoking physicians are less
likely to challenge their smoking
patients overweight physicians are less
likely to bring up the subject of weight
loss or even document obesity in their
charts
ironically overweight patients trust
diet advice from overweight doctors more
than docs who are normal weight
unfortunately primary care physicians
appear to have little to offer in terms
of specifics fewer than half who were
surveyed said they provide specific
advice to their patients
just telling patients to watch what they
eat
is unlikely to be particularly helpful
but many primary care physicians may not
even get that far most physicians said
they would spend more time working with
patients on weight management if only
their time was reimbursed appropriately
maybe we could offer a bonus to refrain
from blaming the victim as one pair of
commenters wrote in response to the
pro-stigma camp
if shaming reduced obesity there would
be no fat people
i want to end this weight stigma video
series with the jaw-dropping findings
of a study that i think best illustrates
how hard it is to live
inside a fat body
if this doesn't foster sympathy
among my medical colleagues i don't know
what will
researchers talked to men and women who
had lost and kept off more than 100
pounds to tap into their unique insight
having personally experienced what it's
like to be morbidly obese and then on
average 126 pounds lighter
47 such individuals were interviewed
they were asked to think back to when
they were heavier and make a choice
if someone offered you a couple million
dollars if you stayed morbidly obese
forever would you have chosen the money
or would you have chosen to be normal
weight no matter what
option number one was i would have
chosen no money and being normal weight
would have taken me about a second to
decide
option number two was i probably would
have chosen being normal weight but the
possibility of having that much money
would make me think about the choice and
option number three was
i wanted to be normal weight but i
really could use the money if i would be
a multi-millionaire i think i could live
with being morbidly obese
one
of the 47 had to think about it
but the other 46 jumped at option number
one
no one
chose option number three they all said
they would give up being a
multi-millionaire to be normal weight
if that shocked you
buckle
your seatbelts
they were then asked about being obese
compared to other disabilities
normally when you ask people to choose
between living with their own disability
or switching to a different one there's
a strong proclivity to stay with their
own for example even though most people
would rather be deaf than blind blind
people prefer to remain blind by a large
margin rather than having sight without
sound they already know how to cope with
their own disability and so their safety
and familiarity
however the exact opposite happens when
the formerly obese were asked every
single one of the 47 said they'd rather
be deaf for the rest of their lives
than obese
every single one said they'd rather have
difficulty reading be diabetic have very
bad acne or heart disease than be obese
more than 90 said they'd rather have a
leg amputated and similarly
about 9 out of 10
said they'd rather be
blind their whole
lives than obese
obesity appears to be the only handicap
where nearly everyone wants to switch no
matter what the cost
to quote one study subject
when you're blind people want to help
you
no one wants to help
when you're fat
[Music]
you